同埋西九嘅代表入場。
我哋落翻會議記錄，畀下一屆去決定嘅嚇。
誒，已備一個報告咧，就提交民政事務委員會同埋發展事務委員會咧，稍後將有關報告咧就會傳譯畀大家去考慮嘅。
誒入嚟同我哋開會喺個時候咧，我都想同大家講一講咧，就係話今日咧，我哋依個小組會議咧係最後一次嘅會議。噉我好多謝大家嚇誒嘅支持啦。噉我哋嘅會議都好順暢。咁咧，秘書處咧將會咧。
咁由於咧，誒，我哋呢一屆都係最後一次會議啦。咁有關西九文化區計劃嘅發展咧，喺來年即係下一屆嘅誒議會咧，噉我想問下大家係咪都係覺得係繼續要成立一個小組，繼續監察啲西九？因
咁如果大家冇反對咧，即係我都當嚇，我哋一致都係要求咧，即係下一屆嘅議會咧都繼續成立一個誒工作小組咧，就係繼續監察西九文化區嘅發展，好嘛？多謝大家，啊，多謝各位誒政府部門嘅代表同埋西九嘅代表出席今日嘅會議。
噉我哋以前嘅第一行咧就係綜合演藝綜合場地嘅最新嘅進展。咁咧就我哋請誒民政事務局常任秘書長啊馮庭淑儀女士同埋西九管理局嘅代表介紹呢個文件。請阿馮得多謝主席。誒，今日我哋嚟誒。
討論嘅兩個議程咧，都係關於西九兩個非常之重要嘅場地，一個就係演藝劇場，另外一個咧就係M+。噉我哋喺舊年三月嘅時候咧，係同呢個小組委員會咧係匯報過，我哋將會咧係誒誒改良一下呢一個演藝劇場嗰個嘅誒設計，將一啲喺第二批嘅一啲。
進展， their provision.
The key components of the lyric theatre.
support theatre, dance and the other art forms with through this particular venue. So we'll be dealing with both of those aspects of this of this project this morning.
And in doing so, we'll be updating members on a series of major dance and theatre programmes which we've organised over the past year in relation to this augmentation of the mission of the Lyric Theatre Complex. So, if members will indulge us, we'll take you through this short presentation. Thank you.
設施咧係擺埋入去，令到我哋可以更早噉樣樣咧係提供到誒更多嘅演藝設施畀我哋香港嘅藝團係使用嘅。咁今日咧就請誒管理局咧係誒誒總行政總監咧去介紹一下我哋今日呢一個嘅誒演藝劇場最新嘅進展。好，Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Just very brief.
因為我們確實有個簡報給你們。正如你們剛剛聽到的，決定是在去年做出的，將麗劇院改造成一個麗劇院複合體，其中包括三個劇院以及輔助設施。
We will be briefing you this morning on the latest state of the design and development, but we'll also be talking about the software development. Because of course, talking about the box is simply only one aspect of the development project. We are looking at the future content, the audience development, and how we can further.
Anyway, thank you very much, Chairman. Members, members were previously informed of the authority's proposal to modify the original plan 1,200-seat lyric theatre by enhancing the design of the planned facilities, as well as incorporating some of the batch two facilities to.
This is achieved through the dance studios.
For contemporary performance, which was also a batch two facility.
And finally, we have retail dining and entertainment facilities included within the building.
We have a welcoming approach. Lyric Theatre commands a prominent location within Artist Square.
The reconfiguration has been warmly received by stakeholders, including the relevant major performing arts groups.
So you can see there on the slide the Lyric Theatre, which is just to the east of M+, scheduled for completion around 2020.
The key design concepts of the lyric theatre, as shown up here on on the screen, which is a concept illustration.
The reconfiguration of multiple performing venues into one single complex not only achieves design efficiency and synergy in future operation.
So the onto the construction progress, the foundation works for the Lyric Theatre and the associated basement have commenced in January 2016 and are on schedule as of today.
finally, a resident company centre with a full range of professional rehearsal, communal and supporting facilities for art groups, serving as a powerhouse for creativity, dedicated for long-term dance development.
include the following: a lyric theatre, which is a high-quality dance-focused lyric theatre with 1,450 seats, with the installation of digital projection equipment for film screenings as a proactive response to the requests from the film industry.
將會易於accessible from the nearby MTRC Kowloon Station and the Element shopping mall through the proposed Artist Square Bridge. The arrival foyer with a large glass facade will give cultural identity to the Artist Square.
But would also advance the completion of the originally planned medium theatre two, and one of the black box theatres in the centre for contemporary performance by at least two years, from after 2022 to around 2020.
The resident company to be located at a higher level of the Lyric Theatre, overlooking the Artist Square, will stimulate the interaction between the public and the artists, and activate the vibrancy of Artist Square, which can be seen at the north of the slide on the screen.
The detailed design of the Lyric Theatre is expected to be completed in around the fourth quarter of 2016, and the construction of the main works is planned to start in the third quarter of 2017, all with an estimated completion around 2020.
第二，ly a medium theatre， theatre focused on medium theatre with 600 seats， which was previously called the medium theatre two， which was a batch two facility。 thirdly a studio theatre， theatre focused studio with 200 seats， which was previously a 250 seat black box theatre， in the centre。
嗯。
當遊客走南向。
The area in front of Lyric will provide public space.
紅地毯事件已經被考慮到，作為設計發展的一部分。
for the people to sit, relax and watch performances at the artist's square.
而原創的都市設計概念，的的西九龍文化區，是保留。
This will be a unique building in Hong Kong with a strong theatre presence and identity along the waterfront.
到的 foyer's of along the spine, the journey gradually leads them to a panoramic view towards the Victoria Harbour.
And up on the screen there is some three D illustrations showing a cross section of the building.
The setting of the lyric theatre will enrich the artist square and build a harmonious relationship with the neighbourhood buildings, including M Plus.
will also be provided to the destinations along the spine, to to ensure the lyric theatre complies with the principles of universal accessibility.
在resident company直接 facing the artist square， which the dancers can overlook the square， whilst the visitors can view the activities inside.
food and beverage outlets with open terraces located at high levels on the south side will also give diners a unique experience with a panoramic harbour view.
所以水front是到右 hand side，和The Artis Square到左 hand side，和你可見的構成那裡，of how the theatres work together，which refers to the previous concept sketch。
Finally, the public spaces, the foyers, the terrace and the public roof deck will not only be valuable and accessible public space to the visitors and artists, but also an opportunity for a variety of events and performances outside the theatre stages.
The central spine, there's three theatres and part of the RDE facilities are strategically connected with an indoor central spine with spacious circulation corridors, which vary in width from four to six metres with their natural light, to guide the visitors to the destination. Barrier-free ramps.
Thank you.
Barrier-free access all over the building.
We have around one hundred and eighty-five car parking spaces.
And that concludes the presentation on the lyric hardware.
And as mentioned earlier, there's a provisions for universal accessibility.
And we have green features. We're targeting to obtain the gold beam rating for Beam Plus.
So just finally, a few statistics. The CFA is around 45,000 square metres for the Lyric Theatre. It's 11 stories, which includes the basement levels.
誒，我接住嚟講會講誒誒喺演藝綜合劇場裏邊，關於藝術嘅唔同嘅軟件同埋內容嘅安排係點樣樣。咁喺誒頭先嘅誒slide裏邊咧，大家都會見得到演藝綜合劇場其實裏邊有唔同嘅空間。噉我喺依度首先誒總括一下喺有乜嘢。
嘅嘅唔同嘅內容同埋藝術嘅形式可以喺裏邊嚟到做。誒，裏邊主要有三個誒大中小嘅劇場。嗰個大嘅劇場，我哋首先咧係設計嘅時候，主要為一啲大型嘅舞蹈演出，譬如話芭蕾舞啊，或者係大型嘅其他嘅誒舞劇嘅演出嚟到做。噉，但係喺呢個劇場裏邊。
咧，我哋都會設置做一啲誒數碼嘅影像投影嘅設施，令到咧誒一啲誒電影業界一路所希望可以有嘅一啲大型嘅誒誒電影嘅活動，或者係電影節，或者係電影金像獎類似噉樣嘅安排咧，都可以喺呢一個劇院裏邊咧係。
一個一千四百五十位嘅座位嘅大劇院裏邊咧，可以揾到誒一個佢哋嘅展示空間。咁喺成個設施裏邊，我哋都誒安排得到會有紅地氈嘅安排嘅。如果係大型嘅呢啲噉嘅活動咧，都可以喺裏邊可以做得到啦。同埋誒誒劇院嘅誒嘅前台嘅地方都係有。
一個全海景嘅一個噉樣嘅地方，咁所以可以做到一啲大型嘅舞蹈、誒音樂劇，甚至係一啲誒電影嘅放映嘅活動，都可以喺大劇院裏邊做得到。咁中間有個中劇院同埋小劇院，六百位同埋二百位嘅小劇院咧，係除咗可以做到一啲舞蹈之外咧，我哋都係設計畀嚟做一啲誒畫。
劇同埋誒小型嘅演出嘅形式可以做得到，咁令到好多大部分香港嘅本地嘅團體同埋外國嘅團體都可以用到呢個呢個誒噉樣嘅地方。咁喺個劇院嘅設施裏邊之外咧，我哋仲有一個好重要嘅住區藝團中心，一個resident company centre，同埋誒。
呢個同時亦都係畀舞蹈團體將來可以用一個駐誒駐區嘅形式，或者係喺一個駐場嘅形式咧，喺我哋呢個演藝綜合劇場嗰度運作嘅。咁用呢啲誒嘅長遠嘅軟件作為目標咧，喺過去嗰幾年裏邊咧，我哋開始做咗唔同一啲活動咧，嚟到誒接觸同埋。
同本地同埋外國嘅藝術嘅團體開始合作。咁其中一個活動咧，我哋叫做新作論壇。我哋喺二零一五年開始一個誒誒一連串嘅同舞蹈嘅活動嘅新作論壇，就係邀請外國嘅編舞家同埋藝術家嚟香港，係誒做一啲唔同嘅工作坊同埋誒誒實驗嘅現。
演出嘅活動，咁用呢個噉嘅形式咧，就係幫香港嘅沒唔同藝術家同外國嘅藝術家咧開始建立到個聯繫。因為我哋呢個演藝綜合劇場要喺二零二零年左右先至會建立出到嚟，咁所以我覺得而家係最重要咧，係培養藝術家嘅誒海外嘅網絡啦，同埋觀眾嘅方面咧，我哋係做得比。
誒舞蹈同埋戲劇嘅演出嘅中心。
誒姚思榮，誒多謝誒主席。
啦，同埋唔同藝術團體裏邊做一啲考察，跟住翻嚟咧就幫西九咧做一做做一啲建議嘅報告。
咁誒，我係好擔心咧，即係到時咧一大批嘅劇場誒推出之後咧，嗰個我哋嗰個消化嘅問題。
誒，我睇到有關資料都係二零二零年誒，呢劇場陸續起好啦。而東九文化中心咧，喺二零二零都係同步誒落成嘅。
多謝大家。O K啊，O K，多謝大家介紹啊。咁請大家委員咧就舉手睇睇有咩提問同埋意見。而家舉咗手有姚姚思榮、馬鳳國、何秀蘭，每人四分鐘連問連答。
較多嘅功夫噉，除咗舞蹈之外咧，喺戲劇嗰方面咧，我哋由二零一四一零五年嘅時候都已經做咗一連串嘅新作論壇，都係同樣嘅邀請外國嘅藝術家同本地藝術家嚟去做一啲工作坊形式同埋一啲外展嘅嘅誒活動嘅合作嘅。咁除此之外咧，喺二零一四年誒誒。
喺二零一五年，即係喺舊年嘅時候咧，我哋邀請咗八個誒誒國際誒出名嘅劇場嘅導演咧嚟香港做咗一個大型嘅國際劇場工作坊節。咁喺裏邊咧就更加係誒誒建立我哋同海外藝術家中間嘅網絡，同埋香港藝術家同埋外國藝術家嘅一種誒合作嘅關係。
誒喺誒二零一五年同埋一六年，我哋分別做咗兩次製作人網絡嘅會議同埋論壇。咁呢個咧係主要係邀請亞洲地區同埋華語地區嘅唔同嘅舞蹈啦、音樂啦同埋戲劇嘅製作人嚟香港嚟到做一個每年一次嘅一個會議，係交流。
大家各個唔同喺藝術個製作嗰方面嘅資訊，同埋將來合作嘅機會。咁呢個係相當之成功嘅項目，係誒將香港變成一個區內嘅一個交流同埋誒合作嘅一個中心。我哋會繼續喺呢一個誒喺我哋嘅劇場誒開設之前，喺建成之前，我哋會每年。
做咗呢個活動，誒繼續嚟到做呢個將香港變成一個國際上誒呢個誒製作人嘅藝術製作嘅一啲同埋交流嘅一個活動嘅中心。咁誒除此之外咧，我哋喺過去誒呢幾年咧一路有同藝香港藝術發展局合作咧，就係送一啲本地藝團嘅藝術總監。
本地中小誒型同埋嘅藝術誒藝團嘅藝術總監咧，去外國做一啲誒為期誒三個禮拜至到兩個月嘅一啲唔同嘅海外嘅考察嘅活動。噉佢哋都係喺香港做誒工作超過十幾至二十年嘅一啲唔同藝術工作者同埋總監。噉佢去外國嘅唔同嘅藝術節啦。
噉我哋亦都做咗一啲誒觀眾拓展嘅項目，譬如話我哋啱啱喺誒五月嘅時候咧，就從一誒世界上唔同嘅一啲誒誒藝術中心一齊咧做一個網上連線嘅活動咧，就係同時同刻喺一啲公眾嘅地方咧，就係做一啲誒誒一個由英國。
編舞家編嘅一段嘅十分鐘嘅舞蹈，噉我哋係喺誒西九我哋自己個地方裏邊做啦。邀請咗一啲誒一般嘅舞蹈嘅學員啊、社區嘅舞蹈嘅學員或者藝術誒舞蹈家一齊喺我哋誒西九個地區嗰度咧誒一齊同時同刻噉樣同網上誒另外幾十。
個誒國際上唔同嘅舞蹈節同埋舞蹈中心咧，一齊嚟去做一個誒就網上連線嘅一個舞蹈嘅表演嘅活動嘅誒喺觀眾嘅拓展方面咧，我哋舊年成功做咗誒自由約啦。我哋做咗十幾次喺誒西九誒海濱做一啲唔同嘅活動喺裏邊咧，我哋亦都係開始。
引入咗唔同一啲户外嘅演出，包括舞蹈啊、同埋戲劇啊，同埋一啲實驗形式嘅舞蹈嘅演出，務求喺二零二零年誒演藝綜合劇場起誒設施起到起到嘅時候，我哋會有足夠嘅一啲軟件啊，同埋同海外嘅網絡嘅聯繫咧，令到呢個變成係香港最重要嘅一個。
need in Hong Kong.
啊，咁呢個你哋會點樣嘅策略咧？喺目前嚟講。
amount of effort that's going in to ensuring that the content is going to be there when these when this venue opens.
但Beyond that, while we look at maybe a third of the activation of the the the time within the venue from
啊！即係同你預期中硬下降。如果係噉嘅話，你有咩策略避免咧？到時嗰個使用率咧下降而出現咧，即係我哋擔心嘅大敗大敗仗工程。
第二個問題就係誒西九文化區嘅管理層咧，會唔會擔心咧？當二零二零年起好之後咧，你哋嗰個使用率咧會有所下降。
或者喺定位上嘅調整啊，如果有嘅話咧，你哋會點樣去考慮，而避免咧佢哋嗰個誒之間咧，即係互相誒可能到時互相競爭，唔係一個互互動嘅關係，呢個第一個問題。
噉我第一個問題問咧，政府咧就現有兩個啊文化中心誒誒，佢嗰個誒定位方面，包括佢個劇場個佈置方面咧，會唔會因應誒兩個區嘅文化中心會作出一個誒分工上嘅調整？
主席，或者我先答咗第一部分啦。誒，其實當時我哋喺誒前兩年嚟立法會攞錢去起東九龍跨區文化中心嘅時候咧，亦都同啊立法會咧係交代過。誒，我哋去推動呢一個嘅計劃，其實係建基於咧整體喺香港嚟講咧文化嘅設施咧係非常之唔足。
其實誒，自從即係市政局嗰個區域市政局兩個誒市政局嘅年代起咗一大批嘅文化中心，即係最近期落成嘅已經係誒元朗劇院啦、誒葵青劇院呢一啲之外咧，已經好多年啦，十幾年嚟咧，我哋係冇再起個新嘅大型嘅文化中心。咁所以一路以嚟咧喺誒。
文化藝術界無論係社區咧，都係非常之熱切咧，係希望有更多嘅文化藝術設施。其實喺文件裏邊咧，誒西九管理局亦都交代咗，無論係邊一個嘅呢一個嘅art form咧，都係非常之覺得香港嘅場地係唔足夠嘅。咁所以經過咗好多年嘅規劃咧，東九龍嗰個跨區文化中心咧，中
上馬噉，我哋其實定位咧，其實係好大嘅分別嘅，因為大家都明白西九文文化區佢哋係嘅定位係放即係立足香港放眼世界，佢哋係希望吸納全世界最精嘅一啲嘅文化表演嚟香港。我哋東九龍嘅跨區文化中心咧，其實都係一個本地嘅設施，等同於我哋其
其他嘅一啲嘅地區嘅文化中心，好似誒沙田大會堂啊、荃灣大會堂啊等等，咁變咗佢其實主要咧都係服務翻本地嘅劇團，同埋係本地當其實東九龍誒黃大仙九龍城，同埋係觀塘，甚至將軍澳幾個地區嘅市民，同埋係佢哋嘅一啲嘅團體嘅需要。
咁所以大家嘅定位係相當之唔同嘅，而且實際上喺香港嚟講，整體咧係有呢一個需要係需要更多千二至千四位嘅呢一啲嘅啊表演劇場，同埋一啲黑盒嘅劇場。咁所以整體嚟講，個分工係噉樣樣。咁如果就住第第二個問題，姚議員問嗰個關於西九自己個定位咧，或者我請阿袁。
先打一打。阿餘生。Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I'll start. Actually, just to to emphasise the point here, our approach is very different to the LCSD approach of a venue for hire. We will be activating the venues as we already do with the nursery park, and what we've tried to show you in this presentation is the.
下一位馬逢國。
地咧係發展得最快嘅，投投資亦都最多。
events that we organise ourselves, that leaves two thirds which will be available for other international groups, other quality domestic groups to come in and use the venues, and again.
activate the centre. What we need to do on top of that, frankly, is develop the audience interest in what's coming inside the venue, and that, to my mind, is equally important to having the performing side. You've got to have the audience to look at it as well. So we're working on both sides.
for that reason we'll be looking at getting resident company facilitation within the Lyric Theatre complex so that there will be a permanent presence with the opportunity for particularly for dance to take on this site and activate it which I think is is something that the dance community has told us is very much in
the the artistic team are working already with those potential hirers and potential unit users to make sure that they are aware of what we're doing because they need to know what how the theatres will be operated, what their sizes are, what the opportunities are in terms of dance and theatre performances, so that when we open the facility into
二零二零或二零二一，會be able to have a full season of programming within a within all three theatres in the Lyric Theatre. So the programme is much more proactive. In other words, we don't wait for people to come to us. We go out and find them. So we're we're confident that there is more than enough demand to.
誒，多謝主席。即係頭先嗰個簡介咧，我覺得都誒相當即係好啦。噉我都係會好支持呢個方向。當然咧，一方面我又係西九嘅董事會成員啦。咁喺呢度咧，我反而想跟進一下咧，即係特別係嗰啲誒演藝即係誒藝術家嗰個交流咧。噉我我都一路都注意到咧，其實。
過去一段時間，我哋集中嘅西九做嘅功夫咧，就係同呢個歐洲，特別係西歐嗰方面咧，有比較多嘅交流啊，誒誒，同埋即係誒誒，畀我哋嘅藝術家去去體驗啦。咁但係咧，其實喺過去一段十幾年啦，全世界發展，譬如話喺文化硬硬件嚟講咧，其實內。
咁建成嘅場館啊，專注力都最多。咁同時咧，我哋都注意到佢個軟件嘅發展咧，亦都係急起直追，有好多即係創新嘅嘢。咁喺呢方面咧，誒，我嘅睇法認為，我香港嘅藝術家咧，其實都係需要咧，係儘快儘早咧，係同佢哋誒去了解啦，去交流啦，甚至係可以即係。
係部署一啲合作嘅咁喺呢方面咧，誒，我我注意到就係誒管理局喺過去喺戲曲嗰方面咧就同內地比較多交流，但喺其他嘅領域咧就相對嚟講係少嘅。咁喺呢方面有冇咩部署，有冇咩打算咧？咁咁另外一個方面咧就係誒，隨住而家即係內地提出一個。
國家嘅戰略就係一帶一路啦，咁誒特區政府都有一定嘅誒，即係回應同埋作出準備。噉我亦都好想問下咧，即係譬如管理局喺呢方面誒有冇開始去思考或者作出一啲誒誒考慮去部署？咁事實上咧誒，無論係東南亞又好、南亞又好，以致到中亞地區，即係中。
而家嗰個攻下咧。
噉樣，OK，誒何秀蘭。
其實嗰個條例未改，仲有個消防條例喺度。
即係引入外邊嘅即係南亞或者誒即係一帶一路嘅文化進入香港。我諗頭先都答咗你㗎啦，如果有補充，你下一次再問啦，何修南。
咁如果你我哋成日都話，你淨係得西九係冇用㗎嘛？你要有一個文化產業嘅後勤基地，同埋畀新人新劇團去自己長大。
唔係嘅話，大家都承認呢個事實係不足，即係嗰個做文化後勤基地嘅地方係不足嘅時候，你點樣同政府去講，去令到嗰個工下係可以幫到文化產業發展？
有好多小劇團喺嗰度自己鍛鍊緊自己，喺嗰度做緊小黑盒劇場，咁亦都有live house喺工下嗰度。但係我我估西九管理局你都知，即係尤其是秘書長你都係政務官嚇。
係去掃呢啲新嘅劇場。第一，即係live house係冇可能做到啦。其實香港而家冇乜地方可以畀佢哋啲band生做live house。第二咧，就係黑盒劇場咧，即係亦都係唔啱呢個工下嘅用途。
東地區咧，其實佢哋嘅都好有文化特色嘅，而正正喺呢啲地區嚟講咧，過去即係香港同佢哋喺文化交流嚟講，相對講係少嘅嚇。咁喺呢方面，我哋有我哋嘅好大嘅人數係少數族裔，噉佢哋都係來自呢啲地區嘅。咁喺呢方面，譬如話誒西九又會唔會作出一啲思考？
或者係部署去誒強化，起碼我哋利用本地已經有嘅資源，然之後咧去進一步咧考慮，譬如同嗰度誒開拓一啲交流啊、誒合作啊，或者針對嗰度嘅誒誒文化咧，係作一啲引入嘅介紹啊，讓即係香港社會咧係多啲瞭解咧。多謝主席。
誒，餘生誒，我簡單補充下誒，多謝馬員嘅誒嘅意見誒，喺同內地個交流嗰方面咧，我哋覺得係其實係重中之重。頭先我個喺個介紹裏邊咧，有一個重點嘅項目叫做誒網誒叫做製作人網絡會議。咁呢一個咧，其實我哋個設計嚟到做咧，其實主要喺亞。
洲地區特別喺華語地區裏邊嘅誒藝術嘅製作人嘅一個網絡嘅會議。噉我喺裏邊咧就邀請咗華語地區為主嘅一啲製作人咧嚟到做一個交流。事實上咧，我哋喺兩次嘅會議裏邊咧，發現咧就其實誒誒喺內地裏邊嘅發展咧，其實係最大最。
最大同埋最快，亦都有好多誒歐洲或者美國嘅製作人係好希望經過香港作為一個誒平台咧，可以瞭解多啲內地嘅發展係點樣樣。咁喺經過兩次嘅會議之後咧，我哋而家決定咧喺下半年裏邊咧有一個小型嘅會議咧，我哋就會去誒國內嚟到做開始做一個分會。
嘅會議噉，我哋咧會繼續咧就喺國內裏邊誒誒建立多啲呢方面嘅網絡，希望香港亦都可以維持到一個一個窗口嘅作用，可以作為一個世界同埋誒誒誒內地嘅一個連結嘅其中一點。誒，至於喺嗰個誒「一帶一路」嗰方面，喺我哋過去呢幾年喺。
誒，國內嘅唔同嘅探訪裏邊咧，喺唔同嘅合作者同埋藝術家同埋政策制定者裏邊咧，都提議過好多關於一帶一路，我都聽過有好多唔同呢方面嘅活動。噉我哋希望可以喺來年裏邊咧，我哋可以計劃同埋構思喺呢方面，香港喺表演藝術可以扮演嘅作用係點？
係啊，唔該，主席。誒嗱，呢呢個誒演藝綜合劇場咧，裏邊都有個黑盒劇場嘅，我留意得到二百五十個座位。咁黑盒劇場即係好多時咧，就係畀啲新劇團去做鍛鍊啊。但係你得一個其實係唔夠啦。咁喺宮下嗰度咧，其實而家。
咁喺呢一方面，即係嚟自政務官背景的秘書長同埋行政總裁，即係你哋點樣去解決呢個問題咧？你係咪覺得喺而家呢個綜合嘅誒劇場嗰度有一個黑盒就可以足夠成個香港發展？即係如果唔...
舞蹈係咪優先使用嘅咧？唔同嘅表演形式，佢嚟申請嗰個。
增嘅指標，噉就可以幫到好多小團體喺工廠大廈裏邊自己鍛鍊自己咯。好多謝你意見，陳志全。
Earlier from from Miss Ho is is a sort of black box concept. So those sizes have been determined really in consultation and discussion with the the theatre groups and the dance groups. In terms of priority.
好，秘書長。哎呀，主席，誒，即係喺呢一個將工廈改變做一個表演場地嘅用途咧，呢一個係一個比較大嘅同埋困難嘅問題，都需要跨局嗰個嘅協助。咁但係似乎暫時嚟睇咧，誒，要解決到呢一個消防條例嗰個嘅困局咧，係比較困難。我哋最近能夠。
改變到咧，就係話喺一啲嘅所謂誒誒大疆圖嗰度咧，用改動嘅時候，用去一啲叫做視覺藝術嘅藝術家，可以喺工下咧去做呢一個嘅studio。呢一個我哋誒突破到有個缺口，但係真係要開放畀誒有觀眾入場嘅一啲嘅live house或者係誒black box咧，仲係。
係有一個好大嘅困難。噉我哋嚟睇咧，民政事務局嚟講咧，我哋嘅行緊一條路咧，就係由我哋去提供一啲場地，譬如話將一啲舊嘅學校，好似大埔官立中學，佢已經係即係唔再營運啦。我哋將佢變為一個嘅誒誒藝術嘅誒aspect。再而家亦。
都係攞到一個資源咧，係將我哋大埔文娛中心本嚟有一個嘅排練室咧，我哋將佢改咗成為一個小嘅黑盒劇場。咁等到喺大埔誒呢一個嘅誒觀立中學變身咗嘅藝術場地裏邊，營運嗰幾十個嘅表演藝術家咧，可以用到喺隔離嘅啫，就係用到呢個黑盒劇場去做一個排練。
同埋表演，噉我哋都係循住用活化呢一啲舊嘅學校嘅方向去做，但係頭先啊海員講嗰種方法咧，係真係相當之困難，因為佢個消防條例所規限咗。咁但係喺西九嚟講咧，除咗而家講呢一個演藝綜合劇場裏面嘅黑盒咧，其實仲有幾個黑盒咧係計劃當中，有一個就喺Free Space咧，亦都係。
興建緊嘅啊！主席唔好意思咧，我得翻三十秒咧嚇，唔好意思嚇，秘書長嗱，陳茂波局長咧就喺網誌嗰度都寫咗㗎啦，就覺得應該用多啲工廠大廈去做一個文化產業嘅後勤基地。咁消防條例喺度，我哋係同意嘅，但係其實工廠以前都有好多工人喺樓上。
翻工即係嗰個人數啊，其實唔會少得個黑盒劇場嘅。噉我就係希望即係跨部門，大家快啲去檢討嗰啲條例，即係譬如就將呢啲誒誒劇團啊、小藝團咧開放去樓下嗰即係二三層嗰度誒，有足夠嘅誒圖。
係多謝主席嗱。今次呢一個誒演藝綜合場劇場咧，就係用一個三劇場嘅模式啦。咁西九就話個最大嘅好處就係提早最少兩年可以提供最多嘅表演設施。但係當初我哋就知道呢個計劃都係好多原因啦，其中一個原因就。
就係慳錢嘅，噉我記得舊年咧，我睇翻啲會議記錄都有議員問過，究竟而家呢個噉嘅操作咧係慳咗幾多？噉佢就話誒，當其時嘅答咧就係要待而以演藝綜合劇場完成詳細設計之後，先至可以得出。咁呢個詳細設計就喺二零一六年。
完成㗎啦。咁而家係咪已經完成咗咧？叫做咁呢條數計到出嚟未咧？同埋究竟而家成個呢個嘅變化嗰個表演場地，究竟係成個故事係多咗定少咗咧？我想畀個大圖畫畀大家，因為個演藝劇場就多咗二百五十個位，但係個黑盒咧又少翻五十個位。
咁但係有冇其其他本來你係有冇係呢個操作之後係少咗嘅咧？咁呢個係第一組問題。另一個問題就係關於呢個劇場本來就一個好，我覺得係個舞蹈館咁啦。當然而家你都係話以舞蹈表演為主主嘅場館，噉。
因為。
and the whole thing's a sham.
O.K. 下一個，毛孟靜。
但係，might not be enough audience。
to that effect, that's what you said, and.
Coming in from the wider China opportunities, both long haul and short haul.
There could be some oversupply, and in any case, your black box theatre would be duplicating quite a bit of effort on the part of.
discussions already with the dance and theatre groups. Dance, in terms of lyric theatre and particularly the dance centre, will have the priority. That's that's the commitment. But of course, with three theatres in one, we we will also be able to accommodate theatre and other uses like cinema. Anything.
你會 be developing audience interest and so on， but I I do have this worry and that is either we don't seem to have enough supply of cultural performances in Hong Kong or we may be facing a glut.
you know not too well-known artists, on at the district level. So exactly what you think you're anticipating when everything's open, you may have plenty of performances.
優先次序又有冇咧？譬如你又裝咗電影播放設施啊，咁嗰啲係咪等冇人跳舞、冇人做劇，你先至去畀電影？定係大家大家去爭搶？我要電影金像獎，噉我就mark咗你嗰日就要你即係就係做嗰樣嘢啦。咁同埋其實啲音樂嗰啲表演場地都未有。
啦，同埋香港要誒演唱會嘅場地都好缺乏。你個名叫咩唔緊要嘅，即係紅磡體育館噉，最後都係演唱會嘅啫。咁但係，譬如呢個劇場會唔會都係有冇一啲即係都係個優先啦，或者演唱會要嚟爭得唔得嘅咧？噉樣好啊，請回答。Mr. Chairman，A couple of things there. Yes.
We will be coming up with the costing. Obviously, we have to before we release the tender. But I can't realistically give you details at this stage because that would compromise our tender arrangements. And frankly, as we said, the final detailed design will only be ready by the end of this year anyway. So when when that's in place, we will of course let members know. That's for sure.
On the the change in in size, what we've tried to do in terms of the number of seats is optimise the size based on feedback that we've had from the theatre groups, from the dance groups, such that they've advised us what is the best size for their type of use. So, for example, the
Lyric Theatre itself at 1450 is considered to be about the optimum size for a dance theatre in Hong Kong at this stage. The medium theatre at 600 seats again is considered to be an appropriate size for a slightly larger than black box operation, and then the small theatre at 250, as we heard.
This in fact is one of the most important aspects of our management of the site. We will have of course advanced booking arrangements, with priority being given to dance for the Lyric Theatre in particular. But within that, of course, there will be capacity for us to take advanced bookings for cinema, for theatre and for other users.
We're now looking at about an eighteen-month advance booking programme, so we'll know well in advance what the usage is likely to be for any particular theatre within the complex. And again, this is something that we've been talking already to the potential hirers and the potential users. There'll be a mix of
events that we programme ourselves, which get certain priority.我我想知其實有冇一個指引，就係係乜乜嘢表演都可以嚟申請，定係舞蹈、話劇，定係音樂會，有冇個分數嘅唔同噉樣？Yeah, of course, those guidelines will be published as well, and that's why we're having these discussions.
Of course, Hong Kong needs a stronger cultural development, and it's gratifying to hear Mr. Pascoe saying just now the content's there, and we'll be having four-season programming. We won't wait for people to come; we'll go to the
冇危險。
即係大家都知道。
咁頭先咧，阿馬逢國議員咧。
議員好好唔滿意佢哋啦，你可以提早收工啊，主席。
roughly 25 to 30% of the visitation came from the mainland.
We are doing projections, but we're not ready yet to come out with those figures.
呢個文化藝術嘅創作自由啊，表演自由係好重要。
啊！主席啊，我我唔係呢個委員會啦，不過我都好關心呢件事。
what works, what doesn't work, what attracts different types of people. So we've done all sorts of different programming.
20%、80%、whatever， but that is certainly. But you mean you can't tell as of today? No, you can't because at the moment that audience doesn't exist.
就話叫我哋香港就同內地嗰啲藝術啊文化界加多啲溝通。喂，噉你同阿何韻詩溝通下先啦，好唔好啊？
That's the whole point. We have to drive that audience development, and that's one of the key opportunities that we have. The number of, I'll just give you a small example. When we did the Sig exhibition.
噉就出咗咁大件事嚇，嗰日我走到去嗰度上環嗰度嚇，都一水深水深岸，望都望唔到啊！我唔知你有冇去啦，你哋個阿餘生買都買唔到去啊，多人多到。
我諗，The whole point is that if you have quality productions, I firmly believe the audience will come. And bearing in mind our wonderful, wonderful location at the end of the high-speed rail link, our audience base doesn't have to be just Hong Kong. It can be people coming in from Southeast Asia, as we heard earlier. It's coming in from the Pearl River Delta.
We've got the opportunity because of our location to develop new audiences that perhaps have not even considered coming to to Hong Kong. You know, the vision for this is rather like what you would see in London or New York, where the audience doesn't just come from London or New York, it comes from the home counties, it comes from the wider area around New York.
It comes internationally. Are you projecting any percentage, say half or less than half of the audience will be from Hong Kong? That's what we're looking at at the moment. I think it would be premature for us, two years, three years ahead of opening the facility, to be able to say we're going to have.
那係一個部分，係我們嘅學習經驗，即係有明顯嘅大陸遊客嚟香港參加活動嘅。當我們做幼稚園公園、Free Space 程度，我們見到大陸遊客嚟參加，而且我哋一直講，幼稚園公園係畀我哋嘅試驗場，畀我哋見到。
Developing different audiences, and we'll continue to do that over the next few years. And you don't even have a base number to work on. Say as of today, as of now, you're expecting ten percent. No, of the local audience. I don't speculate on these things. Seriously. No. But you you have to do some projections.
咁個問題就係噉樣㗎嘛。咁頭先又話阿柏志高先生又話：，誒，第日咧五成嘅人喺大陸嚟啊。主席，喂，噉係咪我哋嗰啲節目係要去符合到大陸嗰啲口味啊？第日即係嚟到嗰陣時，哇！慘啊！主席得嚟到我，我即刻都要散場啊！我講埋即係其實表示。
喺度，我都問多陣你先問啦嚇。
阿秘書長，你覺得我嘅憂慮係咪好合合理咧？
都唔知幾擔心個仔啊！翻咗大陸啊，陣又畀人夾埋。你明唔明啊，秘書長？
sales，咁點搞咧？即係我今日聽到你哋講，我發覺你好似即係唔知活喺咩世界嗰度喎，主席。
嚇！咁如果唔係你個個咁多空曬地方養老鼠咩？阿姚思榮議員講嗰個，我覺得係亦自己擔心嘅。咁即係你你明唔明我哋嘅憂慮啊，秘書長？
即所以個問題咧就係即點搞咧？即一我哋對點樣去捍衞？你話個梁振英，喂，你賣本書啊，賣本書而家都周身蟻啊。如果你第日有啲表演啊，主席啊，好似你噏嗰啲嘢啊，要去到第日都話民建聯都話唔畀你噏啊。第日嚇咁所以。
嗰個文化創作自由係點樣去捍衞咧？如果好似梁振英咁捍衞咧，你又唔使捍衞啦。人哋搞幾個月，佢又話寫張寫封信去畀北京喎。所以咧，呢啲嘢冚唪唥咧，一方面又話要搞融合啊，要符合佢啲口味；一方面咧，我哋啲人咧就嚇到黐線嚇，而家又話一國兩制。
名存實亡噉，你又話啊唔係啊？我哋第五成嗰啲嗰啲觀眾都嚟自內地或者嚟自東南亞噉，我哋係咪真係好有信心？我哋嘅文化藝術自由係可以捍衞得到咧？其實未必係秘書長哋去捍衞嘅。如果你賣本書都唔驚，而家全球都個個都講啊，Hong Kong book sellers，Hong
即係嗱，賣兩本書都咁緊張，你陣間搞咁多嘢，個個走上台喺度喺度表演，喺度跳舞嗰啲嗱。主席你都知啦，我唔知有冇人撳過撳過你，叫你唔好講嘢啦。即係你話點搞啊？秘書長，我哋好似講到我哋真係喺樂土嗰度噉。其實而家咧，林榮基啱啱喺電台噏完嚇。
你都笑啊！嗬，你覺得係係係好可笑，抑或你覺得係好憂心啊？誒，主席、長、主席，我能只能夠喺度重申咧，即係特區政府民政事務局嘅即係對於文化藝術嘅立場，就係我哋係尊重創作自由，我哋從來都唔去幹預呢個創作嘅自由，我哋提供場地，提供設
目，但係我哋唔會干涉嗰啲藝團佢哋自己去創作嘅節目。呢個喺康文署亦都係噉，喺西九管理局將來更加會係噉，因為佢哋一個獨立嘅一個嘅法定嘅機構，佢係唔需要受政府嘅立場去。喂，秘書長，我都未同你算賬嗰個咩台灣咩國立大學嗰個，你都要抽咗人哋。
個名啊，淨係個名你都抽起咗啊！你仲話尊重嗰單嘢都好似未處理啊，主席呵，好似阿劉光華都少組處理嘅。唔係阿劉光華都話唔理啊嘛，佢話任由你搞，你你連個名你都驚到噉啊！秘書長，你明唔明啊？嗰個同創作自由係冇關係。喂，人哋自己學校個名喺你個單張度，你都要。
抽起仲話冇關係，我相信好多文化藝術界都好憂心啦。你你你而家唔知道呢個問題啊？你真係好想話第日哇，我哋招攞內地嗰啲人嚟睇佢嚟睇嘅嘢，我冇意見嘅。我最擔心就係你哋就要淨到嗰啲節目係用迎合到佢口味啊。
誒主席，我諗即係喺嗰個誒節目嘅內容嚟講咧，我哋一向都係唔幹預嘅。但係頭先即係提到話嗰個場地嘅需要咧，呢個係好清楚嘅。喺香港嚟講，我哋相當之缺乏場地，所以我哋唔真係唔擔心嚇起埋西九同埋係東九龍文化中心引致到咧係冇人使用呢啲場地。阿阿主席，因為冇人。
即係嗱，嗰個場地其實我都係憂心㗎。嗱，你哋而家有記錄㗎嘛？而家嗰啲表演節目係有幾多人睇？有啲咧好受歡迎，甚至如果外國嚟嗰啲咧就排曬大隊嘅。但係本地嗰啲係咪你自己都覺得即係誒嗰次都唔係好耐啦？政
無師師長都喺度講啦，佢起咁多做咩啫？佢啲冇啲人都唔識睇嘅，啲水準又唔夠啊！主席，你記唔記得佢嗰次講過啊？你整咩新條脷啫？你唔記得佢講過咩？佢嗰次係講啦，即係令到文化藝術界都好嬲啊！你記得，反而係秘書長記得，佢唔係噉嘅意思。佢唔係佢係咩意思？你講啦，即係佢好似好皮一啊，唔知係咪？
因為我九七年我喺市政局就做藝團小組主席，一路都睇住呢幾個藝團。
係國內或者係東南亞或者外國，佢都會飛嚟睇。咁呢樣嘢，如果你定位淨係畀舞蹈咧，
我發覺舞蹈最少人睇，其實喺社會上咧就個個都學跳舞，女仔個個都學跳舞，但係咧就你叫佢睇跳舞咧就真係唔多。近年咧，因為香港舞蹈團咧佢就加入好多兒童舞蹈，咁啲家長啊嚟睇啊睇翻噉啊多啲。
我覺得即係你你應即係頭先問嘅問題，我你有冇個數字？我哋local本地嘅藝團咧，有幾多個可以真係超過一千位嘅個觀眾咧？你自己應該有個數字啊？係咪啊？阿餘生或者阿秘書長，可唔可以回應下？
望直到到將來西九文化中區嘅設施係落成之後咧，無論係本地以及係海外嗰個嘅觀眾咧，都個數目都係會達到我哋希望嗰個水平。好，誒，我都有啲提問，我都同意啊，劉議員最後邊嗰個關於嗰個觀眾人數嗰個憂慮。
幾時本地嗰啲藝術嗰啲水準同埋嗰啲誒嚟聽嘢睇嘢嗰啲人，佢係咩意思？你講講畀我哋聽。誒，其實當時誒政務司司長即係作為西九管理局嘅主席咧，佢只係話即係喺第三批嘅設施，我哋暫時冇呢個資源係去興建，咁亦都要有待於咧，即係睇下個市場上面或者係嗰個整體嘅文化藝術發展。
錢去到邊個水平係支持到呢一啲嘅設施噉，所以其實係從嗰個財政嘅角度出發嘅啫。即係我哋咩水平唔夠啊？師長當時講，佢冇話我哋水平唔夠，佢話即係去睇睇嘅當時去到邊。好人少啫，冇冇話水平唔夠嘅。佢話而家就即係水平比較低，佢話睇下到時起到幾個水平升到幾高咁先。欣賞水平能力。
嘅水平，而係嗰啲睇嘢人嗰個audience嗰啲嗰啲觀眾人數嘅水平，即係個水平唔夠啊嘛。咁噉我哋點提升？無論表演或者觀眾水平，我哋點提升咧？如果唔係到時個水平唔夠，你真係你嗰啲場地冇人去睇嘅。係誒，主席或者先，就算認真啲答翻阿劉員嘅題目問題，即係。
誒，我哋諗，我哋知道，其實過去嚟講咧，嗰個嘅觀眾羣咧個數目咧係誒慢慢增長緊嘅。我哋睇得到一啲數字嘅，雖然話個增長唔係話好急速，但係隨住我哋頭先即係都阿柏志高先生亦都提到，表演嘅水平提高，我哋入場嘅人數亦都會相應提高。
我哋睇到，如果當即係好似阿遊議員講，有外地一啲高水平嘅製作嚟香港咧，其實真係一票難求。但係我哋本地嘅提水平點樣提升咧？其實過呢幾年，我哋真係等咗好多資源落去喺個藝術家嗰個嘅託嗰個嘅培訓，無論係藝術行政人員，抑或係表演藝術家嗰個培訓，我哋都做咗好多功夫。噉我哋希望。
呢一個嘅藝術水平嘅提高，亦都帶動到觀眾羣嘅人數咧，係慢慢提高。呢個就係呢幾年咧，無論我哋政府康文處、民政局，抑或係西九管理局，都係好努力去做嗰個文化軟件嘅拓展嘅工作。呢一個個方向咧，其實係誒，即係正面嘅，嗰個增長係喺度嘅。噉我哋希望。
因為你而家個定位個《La La Feat》大劇院定位係一千四百幾人，我從來都未睇過一千四百幾人嘅舞蹈會有咁多觀眾嘅。噉你點樣去維持咧？其實香港咁耐以嚟咧，我覺覺得咧最缺嘅咧就係嗰啲歌舞劇場嗰啲，即係做。
啲荷里活式嗰啲，譬如西貢小姐啊、誒Pantom啊依啲噉嘅著名嗰啲歌劇、歌舞劇咧嚟香港嘅時候咧，佢攞唔到長時間嘅表演嘅場地咧，佢就有啲唔嚟香港添，因為翻唔到本啊嘛。但係依啲一定會多人睇，唔止我哋本地人睇，真。
你哋點會點樣營運呢三個劇場？啊，阿馮生。
Secondary to the dance use, that's the first point. The second point is that, as Louis has said.
因為依個係需要，但係如果你話比舞蹈，你睇下過去嘅歷史，你有幾多場舞劇可以孭到飛超過一千個座位？
效果都唔同，你哋真係要小心研究下。最後我都想你講一講咧，你點樣營運呢三個劇場，因為冇人問過，我希望留翻個記錄。
within the venues. By having more venues, we can accommodate that opportunity. And the third thing is that by having smaller venues and the 250 seats, 600 seats.
都係一個基建嘅設施，亦都係我哋同舞蹈界、藝術界一個討論嘅一個結果。唔係，我我我覺得你要睇翻、回顧翻過去嗰個歷史嗰個記錄先得㗎。即係我唔反對你做一個一千四百嘅劇場，尤其是畀音樂劇。
功能啲，尤其是嗰電影嗰度咧，你個三system咧都係同一般個system都唔同嘅，係嘛？你睇電影呢啲嘅可能個要求有倒比系統噉樣，呢啲同你平時又唔需要嘅，噉我覺得你個設計裏邊係咪多考慮依樣嘢咧？啊啊，等佢。
誒主席，我做一個誒簡單嘅回應。誒喺誒誒演藝綜合劇場三個唔同嘅劇場嘅設計嘅時候咧，我哋同本地嘅唔同嘅藝術嘅團體係傾得好多嘅。噉我哋傾咗好多，就係而家我哋有九大團嘅歷史，已經有十幾年嘅發展。
嘅歷史九大嘅專業劇團嘅發展嘅歷史，咁其實佢哋好需要有一啲場地係設計畀一啲專門嘅一啲嘅藝術發展。譬如其實到而家嚟講，香港冇一個場地係設計畀舞蹈嚟到用，無論係嗰個視線嘅安排啊，同埋周邊嘅一啲扶持嘅設施，譬如話一啲熱
新嘅設施啊，或者排練設施係冇一個噉樣嘅嘅設計出到嚟，咁所以我哋發，我哋就決定咧，就將呢個誒大型嘅劇院一千四百五十位咧，喺設計嘅時候咧，係主要為舞蹈嚟好做。噉我哋都知道，而家香港嘅本地嘅舞蹈團體需要一個咁大嘅場地嘅時間咧，再加埋一啲我哋。
會邀請嘅外國嘅大型嘅舞蹈咧，可能係會佔用呢一個誒演藝誒綜合劇場裏邊，可能係接近一半嘅時間咧，會用舞蹈嘅時間嚟去做。但係其他嘅時間，好似頭先又都有議員咁講，其實呢一個設施可以攞嚟做電影啦，可以同可以做頭先誒主席你所講嘅音樂劇嘅演出、musical嘅演出啦。
或者其他嘅唔同嘅演出到出到嚟，噉我哋希望可以做到出到嚟咧。其實觀眾嘅培養咧，唔係一朝一夕，亦都唔係話當嗰個劇院咧起好嘅時候就會日日都會爆滿出到嚟。但係我哋依個類噉樣嘅誒劇場嘅設施係需要佢出現咗之後，誒喺裏邊嚟到培養觀眾出到嚟。噉我需誒呢？
基本上你真係寥寥可數嘅，同埋係好特殊一啲好著名啊，或者好大嘅歌舞劇咧，本地製作你先有。如果唔係咧，你local有好多舞蹈團體，除咗舞蹈團之外，其他都係細嘅舞蹈，或者甚至係粵語性質嘅舞蹈團體。即係當然喺城市當中嗰啲係專業啦。
但佢都係未必係長長咩到過天㗎嘛？噉你到時候咧，你真係要真係隨機應變啊！如果唔係，你你你浪費得好緊要。嗰啲座位仲要整到三層嘅時候咧，通常頭上邊嗰兩層你都係都係close嘅。噉我諗你係咪即係要即係考慮即係呢個劇場咧係真係多？
Mr. Chairman, you're absolutely right. The design is all for things like theatres and what have you. But let's be honest, this is not a theatre for a cinema-type theatre. It is a theatre for dance primarily. The opportunity to show theatre, sorry, cinema films and that sort of thing is really
We're trying to expand the capacity. There's a bit of a catch twenty two for any theatre or dance group that wants to get a larger audience, being able to secure the venue. That's the criticism that we're getting on a regular basis. They're saying to us, look, we would like to put on bigger shows, but we can't get the time. We can't get the duration.
They can develop the programme to the point where it becomes more popular. One of the challenges in Hong Kong is there is no development space. If you're in Europe or the States, you tour something into the provinces before you bring it to London or New York, and that's where you do your development. We don't have that capacity in Hong Kong, so we have to build that capacity in, and that's.
兩千。
just doing up.
as we are.
團體一齊去溝通咧，可以揾到一個最適切嘅一個營運嘅模式嘅。好啊，噉我諗依一個議程完咗啦。我哋下個議程就係講Amplus啦。我哋請代表入嚟。
主要係匯報翻嗰個硬件同埋係軟件發展嘅進展，特別係我哋已經喺今年二月咧係舉辦咗第一個關於seed collection嗰個嘅展覽，咁反應係非常之好。咁或者我喺度請誒阿柏切高先生去匯報一下先。
What, Mr. President? Mr. Chairman, as as we did for the last presentation, we'll we'll deal with both the hardware, the current development side, as well as the software, which includes both audience development, education, as well as acquisition for the collection. I would say that.
係，但係我我都有時間咧，都我都想講講咧，因為你依個大劇院咧、大劇場咧，就即係應付唔同嘅表演藝術咧，嚇，甚至電影咧，你嗰個設計上起嗰個acoustic effect咧，你就真係要好好諗一諗，因為。
而家文化中心嗰個音響效果係非常之差，雖然佢已經係改善咗、拆咗之前幾行位、褪咗個舞台出嚟，會稍為好啲個歌劇、歌即係歌劇嗰度，即係音樂廳嗰度。但係我覺得你因為你應付唔同咧嘅藝術嘅範疇咧，佢哋嗰個要求都唔同，佢。
誒，我哋而家喺度誒構思緊，亦都同誒業界喺度討論緊咧。我哋會嘗試用一個誒誒resident company，即係駐區藝團嘅誒方式嚟到營運呢三個噉樣嘅劇院。喺舞蹈嘅方面咧，我哋嗰個舞蹈中心就即係駐誒誒駐區嗰個誒resident company。
centre咧，我哋而家係同一啲誒香港嘅舞蹈團體喺度傾緊，將佢哋嘅一啲誒創作嘅工作或者係誒排練嘅工作，係移到去呢個舞蹈中心裏邊作為一個主要嘅一個誒創作嘅一個中心，咁令到呢啲噉樣嘅舞蹈團體成為我哋誒呢一個。
演藝綜合劇場嘅一個住區嘅劇團，噉，你亦都會將佢哋一啲主要嘅舞蹈嘅演出，亦都喺我哋個大劇院裏邊同埋中劇院裏邊發生。另外，我哋亦都同一啲誒香港嘅誒話劇或者係劇場嘅團體一啲誒主要嘅藝術團體，亦都喺度討論將來我哋嗰個六百位個劇場誒。
甚至係我哋嗰個二百幾位個劇場，可唔可以畀到一啲我哋一啲專業嘅團體喺裏邊咧，做一啲長期嘅，或者係將佢佢哋一啲比較多嘅一啲誒，佢哋嘅每年嘅製作，佢哋嗰個劇季裏邊嘅製作咧，而去呢一個場館嚟去做，令到可以變成一個誒一個加嘅一個概念。
一個空噉樣嘅一個concept，令到呢個地方可以有一個比較誒遠避啲嘅一個誒住區誒或者住場藝團嘅營運嘅模式。我有少少回應啊，好好短嘅啫，就係話咧誒，文康文處對於嗰個誒住場計劃咧，已經咁多年咧，我覺得都未有即係完全。
去總結到個經驗，即係我發覺咧有啲地方好，有啲地方做得都唔係好理想嘅嚇，有好似啲文娛中心嗰度，即係尤其是你依個藝依個大劇場咧，畀咁多唔同側方嘅人去去用咧，駐場計劃未必係適合嘅。但係當然黑黑劇場、黑黑劇場同埋嗰個小劇場六百位位咧係可。
可以嘅，我覺得，但係因為大劇場，因為如果你畀某一個一方去住咗之後咧，噉佢會同你爭啲場地，但係佢可能又滿足唔到個需要嘅時候咧，造成誒又有啲情況浪費咧。你我覺得你應該都係作為一個大劇院噉樣去去去營運，即係去參考外國嘅營運方式咧。
會係係比較合適，同埋誒誒，因為你要應付唔同嘅一方誒。多謝主席嘅意見。我哋而家都係仲係同一啲主要藝團喺度係商討之中。咁由而家直至到誒呢個劇院嘅開始嘅營運咧，仲有大概係誒應該有五年嘅時間。噉我哋會繼續誒同藝術界嘅團。
好，主席，Members。
所以，我們有個。
and will provide approximately sixty thousand square metres in gross floor area.
We've probably completed around 10% of the main works.
作為M+建築物，位於上述的現有機場快線隧道。
It comprises a horizontal block at the lower levels and a vertical building on top of it.
movement induced from the foundations and the building works is a key concern to both ourselves and MTRC.
since the last update, significant progress has been made on the progress of M plus.
The M+ Building and the Conservation and Storage Facility is aims to be completed in the second half of 2018 for opening in 2019.
The M+ Building sets to create an iconic presence for M+ and Hong Kong on the West Kowloon Cultural District site, overlooking the Victoria Harbour.
Following completion of the foundation works in the third quarter of 015, the main works for M+ as I mentioned commenced in the fourth quarter of 15, and excavation and substructure works is now underway.
What's in the collection and how important that collection is. I think that's that's a very major step forward for the the museum as an entity. So I'll pass it on to Jeremy to introduce the hardware and then Dorian the software.
and， to safeguard the operation of the airport express， we're carrying out extensive monitoring and mitigation measures， to ensure that extreme care is taken during the execution of the said construction works。
The design work has been completed for the main works contract, and it has commenced on site back in September last year. And if you go there today, as can be seen on the slide we have up there, the building is now emerging from the site.
噉我今日咧就大家都好繁忙啊，因為三個會都一齊開，所以啊，我哋呢度清靜啲。即係估嚇估不論點咧，我諗可以進行你進行咗介紹咗嗰個Amplus個slide先啦。邊位啊？誒，主席或者我哋直入去介紹咧，因為大家都好熟悉Amplus呢一個嘅設施。今次我哋都係。
gearing up to the opening of a small pavilion, the M Plus Pavilion. This will mark a major step forward for the museum's development. Having a permanent site within the West Kowloon Cultural District will give us a focus, so that the programmes that we've previously had to organise outside the district can now take place within the district.
那會係一個重大發展。另一個重大發展，當然，正如Permanent Secretary所指，最近的藏品展覽，非常受歡迎，有超過40,000人出席，開始了讓香港人知道。
The horizontal building will house exhibition spaces and galleries with a learning centre, a moving image centre, museums, shops and cafes, creator studios and back of house functions. Whereas the vertical building will house a research centre, a curatorial centre and retail dining entertainment facilities on the top floor.
嗯。
壯身。
Thank you, chairman.
Okay, thank you.
excavation.
And we're doing the pile caps.
Right down to the car park level as well.
Okay, I'm pleased to announce on.
We've excavated down to the basement level.
The software development of M Plus.
this is where the main excavation is taking place.
this is the airport railway that runs through the site.
And a few more photographs to show there.
所以你可見，喺度M plus site， sorry，係around here。
video to show members of the site that's here today.
And just to finish, we have a few progress photos of the hardware construction.
嗯。
of 1,510 works of M+ C collection.
During this time period, many of these exhibitions will also feature the growing and developing M+ collection.
And made nine community visits, and this will continue into the next month. And we plan to repeat the programme with new installations and programmes later next year as well.
It ran for about six weeks at Artists Tree in Tai Kok Place, and during this run, it drew about forty thousand visitors. So it was quite successful both with the public, and the critical receptions were also overwhelmingly positive.
Just reporting on a couple of more recent exhibitions that were organised by M+ under the umbrella title of Mobile M+ Exhibition Series. In December 2015, over the course of about two weeks, we organised an exhibition and performance project.
Titled Live Art, it included ten artists from Hong Kong, China, Korea, Japan, Singapore and the United States. It took place at eight different venues across Hong Kong and Kowloon, and during the relatively short period of run, it drew 6,000 visitors and participants.
We followed that up just a couple of months later with M Plus C Collection Four Decades of Chinese Contemporary Art Exhibition, which was just previously mentioned by CEO. It includes highly selected around eighty works by fifty artists drawn from the larger collection.
So with these last two exhibitions, we have done altogether eleven exhibitions since the beginning of two thousand and eleven, including two exhibitions that we organised for Hong Kong representation at the Venice Biennale of Contemporary Art in Venice, Italy.
Now we move on to or into the M Plus Pavilion, which is about to be completed in July 2016. And here is a view of the building close to the final completion. It's the first permanent structure to be completed in the West Kowloon Cultural District.
And M Plus will be the main tenant and user of this building until the main M Plus building is finished and open in late two thousand and nineteen. So over the course of almost three years, M Plus is planning to organise yet more, ten more or so exhibitions.
M Plus Rover is a major learning initiative that launched earlier this year in March. It is a converted container which we are calling Traveling Creative Studio. The container was designed by Hong Kong artist and architect Casey Wong.
And we also have engaged two young Hong Kong artists to create programmes and installations inside, taking turns. And it has engaged many artists, many students and public members. And as you can see on the slide, we have thus far visited forty schools.
Another important learning initiative is Mplus's summer camp. It took place last year in July in Sai Kung. It involved 100 secondary school students who spent three nights and four days with 10 artisan creative professionals that.
來自於各種領域，從藝術到電影、到寫作、到音樂，和建築，而且也涉及了十五名大學志願導師。這項活動非常成功，我們計劃在這個月再重複一次。
另一個 programmatic 傾向是 M Plus 調景係列，我們已經完成了兩次成功的跑馬，於百老匯影城和雅瑪泰，而第三個題目，這個現在將要上線，幾個星期後。
第二個咧，就係嗰個誒。
可能同內地之間都有一定嘅差距。
特點就係吸引力。咁呢個我唔知呢方面有咩考慮。
誒嗰個誒喺區內啊！我哋呢個嘅。
啊！全世界好難比啦，起碼全亞洲或者喺誒呢個東南亞入面。
如果你你能夠去到有個地位啊，譬如係全亞洲乜乜嘢係最好嘅。
吸引力，或者我哋嘅定位本身個差異性，啊，會唔會喺區內有一定嘅地位？
啦，叫做展品啊！喺呢方面，我睇誒有冇呢方面考慮咧？即係即係唔係話誒人有我又有我好多，都係唔係好唔係吸引力嘅。
即係佢會有興趣專誠去睇，當然有嗰啲路過嘅上邊去睇都會有，但係總嘅嚟講咧就係誒佢嗰個誒知名度吸吸吸引吸引嗰個展嘅吸引力咧係相當之重要。
但問題係展品嘅吸引力嚇，噉啊，我唔知道誒，即係誒當局或者係誒管理層方面有冇評估咧？當我哋起好呢個博物館之後咧？
So that's it for the programme. And as Duncan briefly mentioned, M+ curatorial team is continuing to be busy building the M+ collection, which now numbers over 5,000 works and objects.
鄭橋，好，誒各位同事啊，而家舉出手啊，由姚思榮、陳婉嫻、姚思榮咧，誒，多謝主席，五分鐘。誒，大家都誒，最近我睇到啲數字咧，就啲博物館誒，嗰個入場人數咧就唔係太多啊，所以誒，香港。
最近都係準備免費開放啦，啊，繼續誒吸引更多人去香港嘅博物館啦。啊，本來誒博物館係誒即係展示誒我哋誒本地嘅文化啊、歷史嘅一啲好好嘅渠道，但係唔知咩原因咧，即係香港始終都嗰個氣氛咧。
誒頭先講個太古坊有去到有成四萬人參觀嚇。太古坊嘅情況啲唔同，因為佢個商場嚟嘅，佢個人流本身係比較大。將來你睇嗰個誒M家博物館咧，誒某個程度上係可以咁去專誠去睇係嘛，即係同我哋而家博物館有啲相似係嘛，即係。
咁誒，所以我誒即係政府今次抌咗咁大筆嘅投資喺呢個誒西九啦嚇。噉我計好關心咧，即係誒佢嗰個誒展品嘅內容嚇誒眼鏡咧應該冇問題㗎啦啊！即係而家咁咁先嘅眼鏡啊，最先進啊，設備啊各方面會比較好。
噉你先至能夠使到大家對呢樣嘢有個興趣，就算唔識嘅人，即係你睇有啲展覽，所以有啲人唔識嘅嚇。咁但係佢知知名到去去去睇，好似誒前嗰排個清明上河圖噉樣，係嘛？即係好多人萬萬人空巷，一定有一個好清晰嘅有差異性嘅產品，或者叫唔係產品。
The programming.
In terms of.
誒，因為誒西九鄰近就係呢個嗯。
局係去回答嘅。好啊，Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Yes, I think there's there's two points here. First.
By bringing to Hong Kong, you not only encourage local audiences to turn out, but you also encourage people to come in. And I think you ask the question: Have we done any research?
至少好過MoMA或Tate Modern或San Francisco MOMA。那係野心，係第一點。第二點係，
這些projects， and we already know from the LCSD experience that the the international what you call mega exhibitions are very very popular with with the audiences here.
for the the SIG collection exhibition of the forty thousand attendance, roughly twenty five to thirty percent was from either China or overseas, and I would expect we would be able to develop that further going forward.
museum is made up of different elements. It has its blockbuster exhibitions. It has its routine exhibitions within the spaces. You balance the two. You also have outreach programmes. One of the reasons we're doing the outreach programmes now, the education programmes, is to encourage audience development for the future.
誒廣深港高鐵嘅總站啊，我估嘅遊客嘅比例都會有喺呢方面有冇評估咧？誒起好之後咧，個遊客嗰個佔入場嘅人數個比例係點樣？咁誒，如果有嘅話，有冇啲措施咧係可以吸引遊客，使到大家一開嘅時候咧，就對我哋？
對博物館有興趣嘅咧，噉樣啊兩個問題好啊。或者首先要回應一下阿姚議員，頭先有啲嘅即係誒誒講法啦。其實誒過去呢幾年咧，康文署下個博物館嘅人數咧並冇下跌嘅。其實由零九年嘅平均大概一年總入場人數四百幾萬咧，去到二零一四年。
咧係超過六百萬，個增幅係相當之大。正正就係因為喺過去嗰幾年咧，係真係引入咗好多好出色嘅展覽嚟到，係吸引咗好多人。咁誒，但係即係舊年有少少嘅回落，係因為我哋刪咗兩間館，係嗰個藝術館同埋係嗰個太空館，所以個人數係回落咗。但係我哋相信，當藝術館開翻之後咧，嗰個人
人數係會再上升嘅，咁但係姚議員所關注就係話，即係西九我哋用咗咁多嘅資源去興建一間即係當代藝術博物館，佢個定位係點咧？同埋係點樣吸引即係唔單止香港嘅市民，甚至係即係區內，甚至全世界嘅誒誒遊客嚟到去睇咧？呢一個咧就係我想加翻畀西九館去。
That will be very important because we have to educate people about this new style of museum, which is not just a Hong Kong museum. It is very much an international, certainly Asian if not the world class museum that we're aiming for. That's the first point. So in Asia, you'll be able to come and see a museum.
誒。
誒，客。
有限公司。
係嘛？佢係一個。
即係有限公司嘅時候，呢啲藏品屬於有限公司。
角色係扮演咩？佢係咪一個股東，或者佢佔幾多份？
噉你會唔會即係將呢啲嘢靜雞雞咁去私有化咗？
更加即係難難以透明咧。
即係我我覺得噉係咪已經係隔多咗一層咧，令到啲公堂咧，即係嗰個透明度使用嘅透明度更加。
即係我哋作為呢啲都係用公帑去買呢啲藏品嘅時候咧，都係受到市民同埋議會嗰個監察。噉你成立咗呢個？
到the collection， except for the purposes of display， the actual acquisition is done separately from that。哦，有兩個問題，第第一，政府喺呢啲噉嘅有限公司裏邊嗰個。
It depends entirely on the quality of the collection and the quality of the exhibitions that we put on. And I can say that the team in M+ already have an exceptionally good basic collection, which will continue to expand.
嚇！將來點樣去監管咧？我想即係問下政府，你點樣去監管到一間私人有限公司佢所佔據嘅嘢？佢自己賣咗嘅嘢，佢你你佢你都唔知嘅喎，或者你都唔需要話畀你聽，因為佢係私人所有啊嘛。
O.K.噉我都有啲問題，我有兩個即係憂慮，都喺廿一、廿二段。第廿一段咧講關於嗰個Amperus個管治，而家咧你就將嗰個誒博物館啦，同埋嗰個藏品啦，都會成立一分別成立一啲獨立嘅。
Of course, we have to look at both the contents of our own collection. That's why it's so important that we're building the collection at the moment, and it covers the four areas: visual image, art and architecture, design, moving image, and what was the other one? That's it. Yeah, three.
The quality of the collection is what will drive visitation, and I think that's why we're putting so much emphasis on ensuring that we have a good quality collection. But beyond that, we are also developing our contacts with international museums to be able to work with them to bring to Hong Kong.
一個limited company，噉啊啊啊啊，陳小姐你講講啊，即係被説咗。我先請啊總裁介紹一下而家嗰個安排先。Mr. Chairman, there seems to be a bit of a misunderstanding here. The limited company deals with the management of the museum. The collection is not held by the limited company. It's held by a trust which is set up.
on behalf of the people of Hong Kong, that trust cannot dispose of any of part of the collection. That's part of the objective. So it will be as transparent as ever. We will be reporting, as part of the WKCDA annual report, all of the information that needs to be reported to the public. And there is no way that the limited company will have access.
呢個。
做私有化之後咧，佢唔蘇你啦。佢以前嘅承諾啊，誒點樣誒唔會改變嗰個誒對誒個community嘅個個需求啊？佢提供乜嘢服務啊？佢
佢佢嗰個話事權有幾多？第二，即係你作為一間有限公司去做信託人，即係好難想象個議會去揾一間有限公司上嚟解話或者去講嘅。基本上到時你唔蘇我，我我哋呢個議會你都冇辦法嘅。我我哋議會都冇辦冇你辦法。啊啊啊！即係。
誒，Pascal或者係誒秘書長，你有咩辦法解決個問題？Again, Mr. Chairman, the the company is a wholly owned subsidiary of the West Kalim Cultural District. We are the only shareholder, and as such, we the M Plus board is subservient in in a sense of reporting to the West Kalim Cultural.
文化區區區區，所以個structure係非常之清晰。如果你有任何問題關於區
喂，同政府去監管呢樣嘢。首先，我請咗總裁去解釋下而家個嘅誒操作啦。其實喺嗰個嘅誒整個架構裏邊咧，最終嗰個負責嘅咧、問責嘅咧，都係西九管理局。噉我哋西九管理局亦都係喺誒特區政府同埋民政事務局嗰個嘅，即係誒誒。
呢個管理之下啦，咁但係我哋要將來立法會，譬如有呢一個嘅聯合小組係繼續係需要即係存在嘅。西九管理局現任總裁係會嚟呢一度去解話，我哋都要求咗咧，誒西九管理局咧將來就住呢一間公司嘅所有嘅營運同埋佢嗰個誒操作啊，都需要。
要翻嚟立法會係去交代嘅，所以嗰個問責性同埋個透明度咧係冇減低到嘅，即係我哋仍然係需要為依間公司係問責，佢唔會因為佢變成咗一間誒公司而咧佢係話我唔需要翻嚟呢一度立法會去向大家交代嘅。唔係，依個係你美好嘅期望啫，但係喺個法律上嘅時候，佢真係獨立一間公司嚟嘅。
你如果你自己都企喺間公司冇一定嘅即係權分咧，你係難以去監管佢嘅喎。Mr. Chairman, maybe I can clarify two points. Of course, because we're the wholly, it is a wholly owned subsidiary, we control it very definitely. Second point, the director of the museum is actually employed.
直接由Authority， not by the company。所以，The director of the museum is answerable directly to the West Kalim Cultural District Authority， and as such has no way to avoid coming here if members requested。It is very clearly set up that way。The other thing to bear in mind is the West Kalim Cultural District Authority is set up by statute。
誒。
需要噉樣做。
我咧就覺得。
上次問政府，冇答到我哋。
咁呢個一個理答冇錯。
我對呢個做法，我歡迎。特別係一六年開放，我我同意嘅。
當如果我哋嘅佢功能過渡期完成咗之後，成個展停你個定位點樣咧？
你剪定會否開放咩？可唔可開放咧？可唔可租畀人哋咧？可唔可以畀其他民間團體用咧？即係呢個我都想誒問清楚。
我咧就已經心死嘅啦，因為上次問咗之後咧就不了了之，噉啊跟今日一上上Empress咧就講翻呢間咁公司。
點解一定要組成公司咧？點解架牀疊屋咧？即係我哋喺議會坐咗耐嘅人咧，就知道當時間一路過咗之後咧，有啲嘢就逐步逐步咧係變化咗嘅。你剛才講領會咧有一個好典型。
我們係 obliged to follow the the ordinance which established us, and that obviously has obligations in terms of reporting, in terms of accountability, and that that also is set up with the authority of the legislative council.唔係你你講係一一樣啊？你你做尤其是嚟嚟住房屋局，我仲驚領匯都係噉啊，大佬領匯變。
公司法嗰陣時嘅人細神劈完啦，你而家都市嘅時候，你法律上你係監管唔到，除非除非除非你你即係政府喺依啲依兩間細嘅公司裏邊嘅實體裡，你都有一個股份，或者你都係有一個角色嘅扮演。如果唔係咧，你畀人隔咗一隔咧，到時。
未到，而家佢改埋名添啊！佢而家叫領展啊，咁仲大鑊啊，係嘛？Mr Chairman, again, although I wasn't responsible for the link that was done before I joined the Housing Authority, I can make it very clear: the link is a private company. This is a wholly owned subsidiary of the authority, and there's a huge difference.
Between the link and the M Plus Limited, the whole point is that the community owns the link through the shareholding. The only shareholder in this case is the West Kowloon Cultural District Authority, which is chaired by the Chief Secretary for Administration, which has three other principal officials on the board. There is no way that the
the M Plus Museum Limited can avoid being answerable to the public because it is wholly owned by the public。主席，頭先你提到多次提到股份嗰個問題咧，其實即係頭先阿總裁都講咗，呢間係一間由西九管理局全資擁有嘅公司，個股東就係西九管理局，即係佢有呢一間。
間公司所有嘅嘢嘅擁有權，咁所以如果一日西九管理局係需要向立法會問責，呢一間公司一樣係需要嚟立法會係問責。佢嘅將來嘅呢一個嘅董事誒董事局嘅主席，你可以邀請佢上嚟呢一個立法會向大家交代。呢一個係絕對我哋政府係承諾嘅一樣嘢嚟嘅。O.K.誒，陳宇林。
我哋當時係反對你們上市，反對政府賣咗一啲嘢出去㗎。但政府就一意孤行去做。咁當你話佢唔妥，佢獨立公司，我呢間公司control嘅係。既然你control嘅，咪做department咯，想做緊公司啫。即係我覺得都好簡單。你見你control百分之百嘅，做department唔使做個company嚟算。
但你解釋唔到我哋㗎嘛？即係你話自主點點點點點，我覺得即係喺管理文化裏邊咧。誒，我想同上備講或者係阿阿彭志高先生講，你服唔到我哋啦。即係服唔到我做成廿幾年業委工作人咧，係好擔心將來會出現呢啲問題。除非你今日講嘅説話全部寫曬算。
將來嘅必須要翻翻去立法會去監察嘅，即係我覺得你董事局，我哋監察你哋，你點解唔畀翻我哋監察翻我哋？即係呢樣嘢，我覺得佢好重要。如果唔係咧，時間消逝咗之後咧，好老實講，所有今日講嘅嘢就全部冇曬嘅。主席，我本來就我冇想問嘅，你講我就即係繼續講啦。
第二個，我就想問嗰個Amperus個轉停嗰個部分。咁咧就呢個咧就屬於嗱，我首先覺得就話O.K.嘅喺Amperus去落成嘅之前，要做過渡期嘅一個噉嘅轉停咧，我覺得都好嘅，即係呢點係歡迎嘅。不過問題我就想問啦，即係話嗱，你而家呢度嘅誒誒？
nature of a museum.
我哋嘅承諾咧，係唔會話因為咁咧，佢係作為一間公司咧，佢哋唔嚟呢一度交代。B書長，我加多個附件。
即係話，如果當Amicus呢間公司運作某個時間，社會上都覺得佢唔需要存在嘅時候，你哋有冇條件去對消佢咧？
and that is why we feel that this is the best way. But I can give you absolute assurance, happy to do it in writing if you insist. That if you ask for the museum to come, they will come.
Of course, that's always an option, but that's not the intention. Why would we set up a company with no view of continu continuity of the company? I think it's important to bear in mind the purpose of the company.
咧，我覺得除非好似阿陳宇賢咁講，你一係就成係一個department直接監管；如果你成為一間獨立嘅有限公司咧，我覺得你政府係有責任咧，喺有有一個合法嘅身份喺依個公司裏邊咧，係即係即係行使你嘅職權嘅。
你覺得班根本就獨立王國、山寨王、西九管唔到嘅，可能出現咗好多呢類嘅批評，我覺得你應該考慮翻。即係嗱，我我之所帶出呢個話題咧，我想去盡啲留待一個會議記錄，以待將來如果佢變咗個小魔怪嘅時候咧，我哋都有辦法制衡到佢，主席。
誒，再你宣傳Amper時好點都一個好嘅做法，但係呢過度之後係點咧？我想詳細啲。我兩個問題問先，一個就要畀書長答我。係其實誒，多謝陳議員嘅提問。呢個我知道係陳議員同埋有主席好關心嘅一個議題。其實喺舊年我哋翻嚟去匯報成立呢間公司嘅時候咧，喺當時嘅文件亦都係。
寫咗白即係白紙黑字咁寫咗頭先陳議員要求嗰樣嘢。我睇翻秘書處嘅文件咧，你哋嗰個嘅資料簡介第二十七段最後嗰句，其實就係話與西九管理局一樣，M Plus有限公司的工作將會受立法會監察以對公眾問責。其實已經係寫咗喺度。咁今日如果需要我哋再由我或者由啊？
總裁再重新咧，我哋都重新。Amplus有限公司係需要對立法會問責。立法會幾時需要Amplus有限公司或者西九管理局代表佢哋一齊上嚟去解釋佢哋嘅工作咧？我哋絕對係會要求佢哋上嚟呢度同大家去解釋嘅。咁呢一點係可以即係將來引翻呢一啲嘅。
is to ensure that the artistic integrity of everything that the museum does can be properly upheld and observed. The best way to see that is what it does publicly. Everything that the museum has to do, from every exhibition to the operation of the museum, will be subject to public scrutiny on a daily basis. That's the
我明白，發展公司咧，你講嘅。不過就話你一廂情願。我剛才都講咗，如果你得嘅話咧，點解唔唔一定要一定公司㗎？即係我覺得你改個誒一般做管理上，我覺得唔一定需要嘅。不過我意思就話，你哋而家堅持噉樣咧，我就話咁啦。你如果隔離運咗一段時間，文化團體好多好有意見。
唔係，我我都同意嘅，即係我阻你少時間，因為今日都仲係好多時間。即係一句啫，我就覺得，即係依兩間公司你成立，你都係為咗希望保護啲藏品，但係你保護藏品你自己又唔去參與，直接去參與咧，我覺得係就好危險。因為依啲公堂或者係好多私人，因為香。
講你你係西九政府畀錢成立嘅，佢捐出嚟，依啲其實都屬於社會大眾嘅捐出嚟依啲嘢。噉我覺得如果你政府誒冇喺依兩間公司咧佔有一個合法嘅地位喺度監管咧，就將來咧你打官司都輸嘅，係嘛？因為除非你係shareholder係。
我我。
誒誒，主席。
咁誒？
我嘅感覺係複雜嘅。
咁即係對於MPlus咧，即係誒。
誒Amplus嘅發展咧，咁其實我都有一啲意見。
去承擔個責任，去做決策噉樣，噉係唔理想嘅。
即係我又再申報啦！我都係西九嘅董事局成員啦。
opportunities for them to come in and have a look at it, so that by the time it becomes freed up, they will have access to it. So that certainly will happen. 哈，馬逢國。
喺過咗一段時間，即係譬如話喺早幾年嘅開始嘅時候咧，譬如一啲管藏嘅政策啊、採購啊，好老實講，我作為西九嘅董事，我都好有意見。
即係一方面，我作為董事，我好誒覺得我有需要咧，即係即係誒維護翻即係誒西九管理局嘅一啲合理合合法嘅一啲決定。咁但係當然咧，我覺得即係譬如話就住。
中一個shareholder佔幾多個percent都好，好似地鐵噉樣。你唔做嘢你係一件事，但係你其實有個責任去去做。但係如果你唔係shareholder，你冇一個噉嘅合法嘅地位咧，你係監管唔到嘅有啲嘢。佢賣咗咪賣咗咯？佢話我專家話賣，值得賣咪賣咯。佢專家話值得買咪買咯。依樣我應該我我真係想留低嘅記錄咧。
誒主席，我呢度都要澄清一點咧，就係呢兩間公司其實嗰個嘅董事咧嘅失誒人選咧係唔同嘅，所以就就係起咗一個互相監察制衡嘅作用。咁所以即係話M Plus呢間有限公司想做啲咩嘢，其實佢係做唔到嘅，因為最終嗰個藏品嗰個嘅保護者咧係喺嗰個Trust嗰度。
即係個信託人，所以我仲驚咯，因為噉樣嘅時候咧，仲唔知畀到咩人去trust佢咧，我就就我就唔係好trust佢啦。一樣嘢我都寫寫翻喺個會議記錄對。我哋對佢即係你信託佢個人啦，我真係唔係好信係咩人可以信託到。即係你政府公堂同埋捐贈者都係捐畀香港市民㗎嘛，你政府唔去。
去去去去有一個地位，我冇話叫你完全去擴粗曬成個公司喎。但係起碼你都有個合法身份坐喺度開會啊嘛。你而家連開會都可能唔該你啊，阿阿馮小姐，你出阿馮太你出去，就唔關你事啊。因為呢個公司冇你份，噉你好大個股。主席，我哋而家喺嗰個信託公司嗰度咧，我哋都會打算咧係。
放翻一個即係誒民政局或者係誒康文處嘅有呢個好重要。如果你呢個承諾咧，我就有信心。喺裏面，我我哋暫時係打算擺翻我哋康文處喺藏品嗰方面有經驗嘅同事咧，係擺喺入邊一個首長級嘅同事。有信心。唔係唔係唔係個人嘅，一定係要政府即係作為政府嘅代表，佢可以換人係嘛？你淨係揾嗰個人去。
嗰個人都可能真係若干時候都畀人哋河蟹咗，都唔知咩事。主席同意你，不過我第二個問題未答我。係。好嘛？嗯。係。嗯。係。嗯
Obviously, the the intention is it will be a gallery type space, which which is is what it's designed for. And we will, in fact, as part of the opening, be talking to the different gallery operators, the different interested parties, showing them the space. Over the next year or two years, we'll be giving
啊！我亦都喺唔同嘅場合都表達過噉。不過當時嘅西九管理局嘅當事人今日都全部唔在座啦，已經已經改變曬啦。誒喺嗰方面咧，亦都有咗改變嚇。譬如話，當時我作為董事，其實一啲好重要嘅管牀咧，誒我都係最到最後一分鐘先被知會啊，然之後咧要。
咁而家咧，即係譬如話誒，就住嗰個公司咧，即係成立一間信託公司咧。我個人我係支持嘅，無論喺國內港澳，今日我都講我係支持嘅。呢個亦都係好多即係國税上重要嘅博物館嘅誒一般嘅做法。咁嗰個問題咧就係話，即係誒，無論喺藝術界別或者係公眾咧，其實對。
嗯。
新嘅保證有限公司咧，佢嗰個成員嘅委任同埋佢嘅角色。
In terms of the the general direction, in terms of the collection, perhaps Dorian would like to comment on that one.
The reason that we split the M+ Museum Limited from the the trust is to ensure that there is a separation and that there is
Board representation from WKCDA on both to ensure that that continuity exists and there is oversight directly. Of course, we'll also involve the government departments as appropriate. We have appointed someone from LCSD to the trust collection for that reason.
即係西九管理局咧，或者對即係將來呢個誒管藏嘅安排咧，其實都係非常之關心嘅。噉我諗即係誒作為今日我作為民意代表，我都要特別鄭重要提出，就係呢樣嘢咧。誒，我都希望西九管理局係能夠做得好，去滿足到公眾嘅期望。咁其中有幾樣嘢好重要嘅，就係包括呢一間噉嘅。
除咗好保管好，即係負責保管好呢個管藏一個好重要嘅社會資產之外咧，更加重要佢係畀公眾覺得佢係負責嘅，向公眾負責嘅。咁喺呢方面咧，嗰個任命成員嗰個透明度咧，運作咧係誒運作嘅透明度應該要增加，而佢個成員嘅委
任咧，亦都應該有一啲人士咧，係一個公眾問責嘅人士，除咗官員之外，係畀公眾咧覺得即係佢係有一個責任向公眾負責嘅，即係就唔係淨係純粹一啲所謂專家啊或者係專業嘅人士。噉我諗呢個係非常之重要嚇。即係如果唔係咧，我諗。
我我包括我哋嘅同事咧，都即係嗰個反應咧，我相信都幾有代表性。而係業界咧，亦都同樣有同樣嘅嘅嘅質疑，我哋係要去去應答嘅。係即係初期出現嘅問題，我相信以後再出現嘅機會可能都係細嘅。咁但係因為個管藏越嚟越大，呢個資產。
亦都係越滾越大，噉我哋點樣去利用佢？特別係將來咧，我哋仲要同好多其他世界嘅博物館咧，係互相交換啊、互相借藏啊、誒借展啊噉樣。咁呢個係有大量嘅具體工作要做。咁當然仲有一個好重要嘅咧，我一路都提嘅就話，既然佢係一個香港嘅當代博物館，佢對香港嘅當
當代藝術家嘅館藏咧，應該係首先要做好嘅，要作為咧即係全世界裏邊收藏本地藝術家嘅作品咧，比較完整、比較齊全同埋比較好嘅一個館藏，作為一個好重要嘅使命，先要達到。因為如果冇咗呢樣嘢咧，我諗佢就好難爭取到咧本地藝術界嘅資。
支持啊！呢個係我想畀嘅comment。咁亦都希望咧，管方可以回應一下。好啊，主席。呢位啊，Mr. Pascoe，Mr. John。嗯，Yes， thank you， Mr. Chairman. First, of course, I take the point about accountability, and that's why, for example, all the board membership will be published on the website. It will be fully transparent. Everybody.
Okay.
啊！
誒啊！
誒，馬逢國，你再講嚇。
O K，多多謝你嚇嚇。
噉啊，因為今日有啲新同啊啱有新新同事入入咗嚟啦，新入嚟嘅同事，噉我再重申一下咧，今次。
大家有冇反對？應該冇反對啦，嗬，好嘛？阿石議員有冇嘢講？你嘅領導之下，我絕對從二。
and and that's very much our intention as well. And with our growing international reputation, we're already getting interest from many other major museum collections around the world as well.
埋採購啦，誒，我哋必須要注意到咧，我哋嗰個進入市場咧，係可能會對呢個即係藝術品市場產生嘅一啲誒商業嘅影響。
We'll know exactly who's responsible for both the trust and the M Plus Museum Limited. I think that's important. It's got to be something that the public is aware of and and and understands who those people are. So that I agree entirely. In terms of the the collection itself, of course.
I mentioned that the collection currently is numbering at about five thousand objects, and it's bound to grow over the next three years before the opening of the museum. Of about five thousand objects, over one thousand three hundred are works and objects by Hong Kong artists, architects and designers and other creative makers.
So I can say that the core of the collection is very much based in Hong Kong and from Hong Kong, very much in line with the vision of M+ which is meant to be 20th and 21st century museum of visual culture with Hong Kong perspective but global outlook. So I think we're
very well on on our way of creating a collection that is simultaneously locally rooted but with a global outlook. You also mentioned that this is a great resources and assets that we have that will also create opportunities for loanings and exchanges with with other major collections.
好嘛，我我講咗先啦，睇下阿石石議員有冇。即係我想話畀大家聽，今次係最後一次會議，噉我哋咧就會暫時一個報告咧，備註暫時一個報告交畀民政事務及誒委員會同埋發展委員會嘅。咁咧就如果大家唔反對，我哋就會完咗今次嘅會議，就會誒講一我哋依一屆。
係呢一年嘅，即係做。我仲冇時間㗎。有有有有有，我講埋依依依個嘢先，因為你走咗嘅時候，我對空氣講嘅啫嚇。咁同埋咧，我哋誒大家如果唔反對的話咧，我哋都建議咧下一屆嘅立法會咧都繼續成立一個小組去繼續監察誒西九嘅發展。
誒，我我呢個都係希望可以聽到即係局方嘅回應咧。即係其實咧，業界其中一個好擔心或者好關注點咧，我諗過去一段時間唔係太多人提嘅。我諗我今日咧，既然最後一次會議，我都提一提咧，就係即係既然我哋有一個新嘅博物館，有準備要做大量嘅館藏同。
咁特別對一啲即係所謂藝術品嗰個價格嗰個影響啦。咁而家嚟講到今天為止，我相信咧喺呢方面，誒西九管理局特別係M Plus咧，都幾依賴一啲外國嘅誒誒一啲藝術品嘅誒鑑證公司啊，或者係一個評價公司。
知啊，去作為一個誒評估嘅啊，對嗰個價格。咁呢個咧，即係誒一方面係無可厚非嘅，但係我諗我哋都要注意到咧，即係我哋嗰個採購可能會對誒市場帶嚟一啲嘅影響，就避免咧我哋成為一個咧誒誒被即係利用咗作為即係去。
There is.
acquiring art.
artworks increase， and if they are acquired by M Plus.
for the collection, I would also make a point about.
There is a desire among local artists to see the value of their, their, their.
主席，我 just like to follow up with what阿馬鳳 got questions on the.
We're very very discreet about participation in auctions, participation in in direct negotiations with galleries because of that concern. Now the other side of the coin, of course, is that
houses, we quite often don't go through galleries. Very rarely go through galleries. We will approach the the artist direct. There will be a number of months, if not years, of negotiation, discussion to acquire the appropriate artwork. That's for obviously living artists. For
increasingly new separation between less and less separation between local art market and international market. There are new local galleries that are emerging, but Hong Kong art market has just become is becoming more and more international, and they are becoming part of it. 好，阿石二。
The art museum or the M+ or MoMA or whoever, the fact that that someone has been acquired by a prestigious institution like this has an effect on the market. There is there's no way you can you can avoid that. But that's actually a positive thing, particularly for local artists. So it is a balance. Do you want to add anything to that?
影響市場價格嘅一個工具啊，咁呢個係誒西九管理局嘅同事咧喺進行佢哋採購嘅過程裏邊咧，必須要誒經常關注同埋即係提醒自己嘅啊，即係呢個係一個好重要嘅誒誒誒考慮嚟嘅，明白？因為喺亞洲區嚟講，呢一個博物館嗰個。
出現咧係會誒一定會產生影響嘅，咁所以誒，但係我又咁睇嘅。另外一個方面咧，即係如果佢係能夠對我哋本地嘅藝術家、本地嘅誒誒，即係呢呢一方面嘅一個誒藝術品咧，佢有一個正面積極嘅影響咧，我一啲都唔介意嘅，啊，即係呢個係可以對本。
本地嘅藝術發展咧，係會有一個正面嘅影響啊！但係如果我哋係唔覺意，即係不經意地被利用咗去，即係影響咗一啲其他嘅外國嘅一啲藝術品嘅進入誒，我哋呢個市場嘅價格咧，噉我覺得係要注意，我只係作一個提醒嚇。誒，有冇回應啊？係啊，司長。
I'll start, maybe Dorian can supplement. I think it's it's a valid point that we potentially could if we were not careful about how we acquire artworks. But often we will actually negotiate directly with the artist. We we quite often don't go through auction.
artists that have passed on, of course, then donations become very important, and we've had substantial donations. I mentioned the SIG, but we have had others, and that's another way where we get access to items that we need for the collection without, frankly, affecting the market at all. And indeed, when it comes to
then of course the recognition that that gives to them inevitably raises their profile so it's it's not necessary the fact of the buying that's the issue it's the impact of the the fact that that particular art piece has been bought and is part of the permanent collection now that is something that would happen with any museum doesn't matter whether it's
Yes, sure. Yes, a few points. I think it is just the fact that the local art market for especially not so well established contemporary artists is not there, but it is on its way. It is growing. I think Hong Kong art market in general is growing.
And I think it is just part of being being part of the ecology that the museum does have impact, which Duncan has already mentioned. But according to the international museum standard and practice, that we're extremely careful about not revealing the financial transactions and values of the acquisition.
World market, frankly, how much could
The WKCD effect that amount is really is a drop in the ocean.
藝術家， in in lieu of better artistic work， again is all subjective。
新 artist and which at what price and things like that. Because if you look into the art world,
effect on the market. Basically, the amount of money that the West Kaluan Cultural District have is really peanuts compared to the world.
To be collected, if they're not up to standard, they're not collected. So, just just from an ignorant point, sick from my angle, is that do you publish make publication of what you have acquired under five thousand, and is it available to the public?
purely your your your panel members or are they from outside? I think that is more important than affecting the market. If they can really affect the market, good luck on them, because nobody can control the market, really. You know, so so I think the more concern is.
Are we going to buy contemporary artists from Hong Kong, from China? Actually, art is no national barrier. Art is international. Art is global. So it's the choice of the artist is what dictates on the museum. You know. Yeah.
my my concern is not because art is a very subjective subject you know because what is art is all in the eyes of the beholder. My concern is how do you decide who to buy from which
on how the a lot of the venture capital, they they actually bought a lot of new artist painting and boosted up and that's out into the market. I mean, I hope that your concern would not actually do that. And do you have a panel to judge and to decide on which artist? Because are they?
Mr. Chairman, I think that's absolutely right. I mean, we we have a good budget, but it's not world-shattering. Now, if it was, I'd be much happier. But I think the the second part of the question is is is equally important. You know, with the internet and with the speed of communication, it is an international market, and because of that, we we have to be very careful.
in our acquisition policy, so we do have a published policy which indicates which areas we collect in. The curators work very closely to identify the suitable pieces to ensure that the collection is rounded, and then we obviously do have an acquisition committee that advises us on the type of acquisitions and the areas that we
We should be looking at. So there is a process already in place, as you suggest. And I do hope that politics do not come into your selection of artists. You know, Duncan, this is easily happened, particularly a lot of budding artists from from China. You know, and and secondly, there's a lot of
other budget budding artists from Vietnam and other places. No, so I think is we make Hong Kong international is more important than just glooming local artists. Local artists if they're good, they will be in there. Not because they're local artists. You can have promotion for local artists, but not necessary solely buying from local.
no and in fact as as Dorian reported earlier out of the 5,000 odd collection about roughly a fifth is local artists the rest are international artists and that's that's I think reflective of the quality of the local artist as much as the quality of the of the collection as a whole they have to be up to the standard.
Yes, so we regularly update the full list of works and items in the collection. So we do it. We try to do it twice a year, and it is available as a PDF file on the WKCD website. But do you have exhibition of those collection?
OK，thank you。
C。
畀話佢有價值啊！
佢佢呢啲。
我我用到危險呢個字眼。
and share, you know.
你有，因為藝術是通過。
嘅價格只係市場嘅價格，呢啲市場嘅價格可能係一啲投機嘅價格。
咁但係大家都知道蘇富比係一個誒auction company係嘛，一個即係。
唔係等於個藝一定個藝術價格，即係我覺得咧，而家咧，Amperus有五十五千件嘅藏品裏邊，希臘件嘅比重非常之大。
多謝兩，我最後我都誒都有啲意見。第一咧，我翻頭先嗰個管治嗰度咧，我都係好希望咧就寫低去咧。即係我覺得，我作為主席，我都非常憂慮咧。如果政府冇一個合法嘅身份喺兩間公司裏邊咧，呢個係非常危險。
exposing of those pieces, you know, there's so many different museum in Hong Kong. You can, you don't have to wait till the museum to open to exhibit those art pieces, you know. Sure, during he can lend some of us to to to to this lecture council, make it nicer.
我 mean this is no, this is exactly what you have five thousand seven pieces, which you use the money because it's interest also. I mean, and also be there will be appreciation, but the appreciation in terms of value. But then there is also appreciation in terms of of of art appreciation, which you let other people.
In fact, just just very briefly to say, we have run a number of exhibitions. The most recent was the Sig Collection exhibition, both here and overseas. In fact, part of the Sig Collection is currently on show in Basel at the moment. We we will be stepping that up with the opening of the M Plus Pavilion. We'll be able to do more of that in the future.
因為誒，即係過咗兩三二三十年、八年之後咧，就即係呢啲承諾，佢求剛才嘅承諾咧，都唔係一個法律嘅承諾咧。你呢兩間公司咧，佢自己獨立去運作嘅時候咧，可以唔受約束嚇。噉我我我依個係我意見啦嚇，唔想唔使回應嘅咧。第二咧。
就係關於個藏品嗰度，我都好同意馬逢國委員咧對於嗰個憂慮嘅，因為過去我起訴四年咧，我哋最初對誒藏品嘅批評嘅時候咧，上一任嘅C.O.咧只不過話啊，佢係好實好有價值嘅呢啲藏品，尤其是希克嘅藏品，因為蘇富比。
係，係，即係。
係人哋會覺得你Amper是係為欺客而設。
係變成一個希克嘅博物館，依個唔係我哋嘅目的嚟嘅，我相信。
誒，西九管理局咧有一個好具體、好即係誒。
即係你你哋係咪要考慮清楚咧？將來咧係要有一個比較客觀。
咁同埋我都有參觀個誒希克嗰個展覽咧，希克嘅藏品唔係等於全部中國當代嘅藏品。
多吸收多方面嘅人士嘅意見，佢嘅去去做呢個收藏嘅政策咧。到而家呢四年都過咗啦，我到而家都未睇到咧。誒，呢個。
好疏離嘅收藏嘅嘅嘅嘅文嘅政策嘅文件，加上議會，我希望即係下一屆會畀議會同埋公眾知道你哋收藏嘅方向同埋你嘅方法啦，好嘛？
係嘛？即係我哋喺西九嘅時候，我哋做呢個Empress嘅博物館嘅時候，我哋唔係為某一個人嘅藏品或某一啲人嘅藏品去去去做嘢。呢個亦都會影響咗市場嘅價格。如果我哋咁做的話，
佢只不過喺八十年代，佢收藏咗八十年代某一啲團體嚇，對於呢啲誒當代藝術，而係自己誒中國嘅當代藝術嘅嘅嘅收藏。呢個唔係等於全個中國嘅誒當代嘅藏品，而且當代藝術亦亦都係好啱腳步，好好爭議性嘅。所以我覺得咧。
Mr. Chairman, first let me make one very clear statement, which I'm happy to go on record. The museum isn't about the C collection. It was a very helpful start to the collection. You know, getting a large donation of that sort makes a big start. It means we didn't have to put money into a collection, but we almost overnight became one of the biggest and most
important contemporary Chinese art holders in the world. That was a fantastic donation, but it is not the only part of the collection. We've gone on to collect over 5,000 pieces, at least three and a half thousand of which are not part of the Sid collection. So I think that must be put on record. The second part is that yes, contemporary art is contro
That's one of the reasons why we have to make sure that the decisions on artistic merit taken by the curators by the museum is properly protected. I don't want interference from government. I don't want interference from the board. I certainly don't want interference from anywhere else. That's one of the reasons why this approach is so important to ensure.
噉我希望你即係可以盡快可以做多呢個收藏嘅政策出嚟啦。因為以往佢真係話好依賴蘇富比出嚟個價格個價值，呢個即係係好荒謬。
某一個做法係嘛，即係依啲企會議記錄有嘅嚇，咁但係我都好聽到你講咧，即係我哋唔會將個emphasis變成係氣壓博物館啦，只係唯一嘅藏品啦，係嘛，或者仲唯一重要藏品。正如頭先姚思榮議員講咧，即係話我哋都要揾一啲鎮山之寶啊，係嘛，即係你要揾一啲。
好重要、好好熱、好重要嘅嘅藏品嚟咧，令到我哋嗰個博物館嗰個名聲譽提高嘅。噉，我覺得依方面咧，係咪真係將你哋要小心去做嚇？Mr. Chairman，I didn't pick up on this point about the valuation of the collection. The reason that we value the collection
是 for insurance purposes. It's not for the purposes of sale or influencing the market, and that's the only reason that we use international advisers to advise us. It's for insurance purposes only. It has no market impact at all.
咁誒，如果誒冇乜嘢咧，我哋今日咧就完結咗呢個誒即係議程啦。我亦好多謝誒西九管理局同埋民政局咧，依四年嚟嘅咧就即係即係同我哋議會嘅合作。噉我哋都誒有一啲成果嘅嚇。多謝大家，多謝。